All right, so I'll now go to discuss
the evolution of corporate governance in Nigeria and
the culmination into the Nigerian Code of Corporate
Governance.
So pre-1990, the principal company law statute
in Nigeria was the Companies and Allied Matters
Act 1968, which was modelled after the Companies
Act UK of 1948.
Essentially, the Act contained provisions on companies in
relation to the board of directors and the
members in general meeting.
It soon became apparent that that Act in
itself was not enough to regulate the affairs
and activities of companies.
Between the period of 1990 to 2013, many
issues associated with corporate governance failures started to
emerge, and those matters were essentially outside the
legal arena and had more to do with
ethical, concerns rather than legal.
And accordingly, the SEC Code of Corporate Governance
was promulgated, the SEC is the Securities and
Exchange Commission, promulgated a Code of Corporate Governance
in 2011.
Following that, other sectors also came out with
their own Codes of Corporate Governance, notably the
CBN, NICOM, PENCOM, and the Nigerian Communications Commission.
There was an attempt to harmonise all of
these sectorial codes in 2018 with the promulgation
of the Nigerian Code of Corporate Governance 2018,
which has been subsequently amended and came into
operation in 2019.
With the promulgation of the Nigerian Code of
Corporate Governance, the other codes continue to exist
side by side, but recently, as recently as
two years ago, another attempt was made to
streamline those other codes and reduce them to
guidelines, such that the only code that we
now have is the Nigerian Code of Corporate
Governance, which is indeed a code of best
practise.
So all the other sectorial codes have been
reduced to guidelines and where there is a
conflict between the guidelines and the code, the
provision with a stricter requirement is the one
that would apply.
So for instance, if the Nigerian Code of
Corporate Governance says that the tenure of non
-executive directors would be at the discretion of
the board and the CBN guideline says it
would be 12 years, the CBN guideline is
the one that would apply because that is
a stricter provision by a regulator regulating that
particular entity.
So just to briefly speak to CAMA, which
is the Communities and Other Matters Act 2020.
It was promulgated in 2020, as I said,
and essentially it came to replace the 30
-year-old legislation that was passed in 1968
and has a few governance provisions, interestingly, for
the first time.
So for instance, it speaks to having independent
directors of the board or public companies.
It also regulates the number of boards a
director of a public company can sit on.
Interestingly, in February 2023, the government came out
with the Business Facilitation Act, which slightly amended
CAMA and also made a few corporate governance
provisions.
For more details on this, the resources for
this session are available in the link that
will be shared along with this video.